const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",o="civiledu",a=200,t=120,i=[{id:329,question:"The NYSC was established in the year .................",option:{a:"May 22, 1973",b:"June 15, 1960",c:"May 22, 1963",d:"August 20,1993"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:336,question:"Nigeria is a ............. state",option:{a:"Communist",b:"Capitalist",c:"socialist",d:"Feudalist"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:356,question:"Which of the following statements is not correct?",option:{a:"Valid driver’s license must be obtained before attempting to drive",b:"Flowing garment can be worn on a motorcycle or bicycle",c:"Headlights should be used during unfavourable weather",d:"Drivers must not engage in distractive activities while driving"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:54,question:"Most African countries owed their creation to",option:{a:"African Union (AU).",b:"Commonwealth of Nations.",c:"Ethnic and tribal leaders.",d:"European Colonialists"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:147,question:"To ensure the rights and freedom of citizens; the power of the arms of government must be",option:{a:"fused",b:"incorporated",c:"separated",d:"rotated"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:167,question:"The following is the function of a responsible parenthood",option:{a:"care and love",b:"gambling",c:"Drug addition",d:"fighting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:159,question:"Citizenship is acquired by an alien through",option:{a:"registration",b:"birth",c:"Conferment",d:"Naturalization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:120,question:"One of the following is a cause of single parents in Nigeria",option:{a:"slow parenting",b:"social group",c:"nature of work",d:"divorce"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:379,question:"The motherland in the monologue could best be described as",option:{a:"a nation in transition",b:"a morally upgrading country",c:"a socially viable nation",d:"an ethically bankrupt country"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:253,question:"As Mr Umukoro got to Oghara junction, near Sapele, he packed the bus and bought some roasted monkey bush meat. Some of the passengers in the bus followed suit, that day was a good Friday. On motion Mr Umukoro, the driver and some of the passengers were doing justice to the monkey bush meat. No sooner had they started than they were stopped and Mr Umukoro was fined by men of the FRSC. If the fine was proper which of the reasons bellow could be responsible for it",option:{a:"some of the passengers ate the bush meat while the bus was on motion",b:"Mr Umukoro, the driver was driving and eating at the same time",c:"They were not supposed to eat monkey bush meat because they can contact the Ebola virus from it.",d:"They were not expected to eat and any kind of meat on a good Friday"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:320,question:"The former National anthem begins with.......................",option:{a:"Nigeria We Hail Thee",b:"Arise O Compatriots",c:"I pledge to Nigeria my Country",d:"So help me God"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:381,question:"Based on the monologue above, the best approach to curb moral decadence in the motherland is by",option:{a:"value re-orientation",b:"introducing war against corruption",c:"legalizing capital punishment",d:"sending corrupt officials on exile"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:94,question:"When the national flag is flown half mask, it is a sign of national",option:{a:"centenary celebration",b:"children’s day",c:"independence",d:"mourning"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:185,question:"An agreed set of rules prescribing the governance of a country can be called the",option:{a:"constitution",b:"charter",c:"manifesto",d:"programme"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:193,question:"Which of these is a type of parenthood",option:{a:"single parenthood",b:"ethnic parenthood",c:"village parenthood",d:"clan parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:64,question:"How many senators are elected from each state in Nigeria?",option:{a:"2",b:"3",c:"4",d:"5"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:129,question:"One of the following is not a political party",option:{a:"PDP",b:"APGA",c:"ANPC",d:"CPC"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:35,question:"Civil societies are vital for the promotion of popular participation because they are",option:{a:"profit - oriented organizations",b:"engaged in developmental programmes",c:"involved in political education",d:"formidable oppositions to government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:103,question:"Local government is the ............... tier of government",option:{a:"1st",b:"2nd",c:"3rd",d:"4th"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:135,question:"The president belongs to ............... arm of the government",option:{a:"Executive",b:"Judiciary",c:"Military",d:"Legislature"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:21,question:"What value did Imoh demonstrate.",option:{a:"Tolerance",b:"Confidence",c:"Fair play",d:"Honesty"},section:"Imoh lived with her parents in Kakuri. They were good citizens who detested all forms of immoral acts. Both at home and in school, Imoh had been taught the virtues and values of a good citizen. However, while in a bus on her way home from school, the conductor forgot to ask for her fare. She knew that the right thing to do was to pay even when the conductor had forgotten to collect the fare. She also knew that there were other things she could do with the money if it was not paid, but she did what was expected by informing the conductor and paying the fare.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:136,question:"The process whereby an individual choose to favour a person who come from his family or tribe over other people or tribes is known as",option:{a:"stereotype",b:"ethnicity",c:"nepotism",d:"favouritism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:411,question:"Which of the following statements best describes Human Trafficking?",option:{a:"Recruitment of youths as casual workers",b:"Desperate desire by youths to travel abroad",c:"Buying and selling of humans for selfish purposes",d:"Transportation of gods and service through human portage"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:112,question:"The 219 chibok girls were ................ while ..............",option:{a:"abducted, praying in the mosque",b:"kidnaped, praying in the church",c:"abducted, wondering along the street of chibok town",d:"kidnaped, preparing to write their WAEC examination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:172,question:"A constitution that is very easy to amend is called a ...... constitution",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"an easy",d:"simple"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:206,question:"The process of enlightening or training citizens on their rights and responsibilities is known as",option:{a:"Workshop training",b:"Citizenship Education",c:"Political Education",d:"Citizenship Rights"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:118,question:"The following factors are responsible for drug abuse except",option:{a:"family upbringing",b:"high stress level",c:"poverty",d:"foster parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:291,question:"It is often said that public servants cannot be held responsible for their actions. This principle denotes .................",option:{a:"anonymity",b:"civic irresponsibility",c:"accountability",d:"neutrality"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:134,question:"Laws are interpreted by the",option:{a:"Judiciary",b:"President",c:"Legislature",d:"Executive"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:426,question:"A major civil society group which campaigned against military rule prior to the advent of the Fourth Republic in Nigeria is the",option:{a:"Campaign for Democracy",b:"Save Nigeria Group",c:"Civil Liberties Organization",d:"National Democratic Coalition"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:84,question:"Which of the following is not a function of political parties?",option:{a:"Aggregation of opinion",b:"Educating the government",c:"Interest articulation",d:"Unifying factor."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:273,question:"The attitude of the crowd towards, the sick man was that of ............",option:{a:"indifference",b:"friendliness",c:"hospitality",d:"political apathy"},section:"A certain man came to visit his friend at Shomolu one early morning. Unexpectedly the man fainted and slumped. He lay on the floor for several hours and looking lifeless. The crowd and even the friend he came to visit kept a reasonable distance from him. No one came to his rescue or even attempted to touch him. As luck would have it he regained his strength after about five hours and managed to go back to his house",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:22,question:"Conflicts are better resolved in the society through",option:{a:"tribunal",b:"litigation.",c:"dialogue",d:"the court"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:128,question:"One of the following is not a pressure group",option:{a:"National Association of Nigeria Student (NANS)",b:"Nigeria Labour Congress (NLC)",c:"Academic Staff Union of Universities (ASUU)",d:"Committee for Defense of Human Right (CDHR)"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:208,question:"The illicit or illegal business in the sales and 	transportation of human beings for economic and other selfish purposes is known as",option:{a:"Human capital development",b:"Human traffic rule disobedience",c:"Human trafficking",d:"Mans inhumanity to man"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:360,question:"The general attitude of government and society towards cultism is that of",option:{a:"affection",b:"sympathy",c:"abhorrence",d:"support"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:335,question:"The killing of NYSC members in certain parts of the country  ................",option:{a:"Contradicts the goal of establishing the scheme",b:"Is in line with the aims of establishing the scheme",c:"Is not a serious matter",d:"Enhances national unity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:268,question:"Political Apathy can lead to",option:{a:"very fast pace of development",b:"the emergence of sound democratic government",c:"wrong set of people coming into power",d:"development of sound political culture"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:137,question:"When a group of people believe in and keep to certain norms, values and ways of life of their community since its creation, we call this .................",option:{a:"religion",b:"stereotypes",c:"traditions",d:"custom"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:8,question:"Based on the statements above, the decision of the student on having a bullet proof vest shows that cultism",option:{a:"spreads fear and terror.",b:"is a training ground for armed forces.",c:"breeds courageous graduates.",d:"propagates self - defence."},section:"NEWS: ‘Rival Cult Group Killed Ten on Campus’<br> 	STUDENT: I will definitely need a bullet proof vest before I can go back to the Campus.<br>",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:345,question:"The process of enabling someone to perform an action which adds value to his/her life is known as",option:{a:"employment",b:"recruitment",c:"socialization",d:"empowerment"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:75,question:"The International Court of Justice is located in",option:{a:"Britain.",b:"Netherlands.",c:"Nigeria.",d:"Norway."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:100,question:"The responsibility of protecting past and present high ranking government officials falls on ...............",option:{a:"police",b:"army",c:"civil defense corps",d:"SSS"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:45,question:"The condition of disorderly behaviour exhibited by the mob in the story best describes the",option:{a:"ineffectiveness of the police",b:"breakdown of law and order",c:"importance of ministerial position",d:"need for stiffer security measures"},section:"Chief Bilisi was a prominent politician and honourable minister in Kantoga Republic. He had sponsored several candidates to power and made them to swear oath of allegiance to him. In return, they awarded contracts and offered financial and material assistance to him at the expense of the public. This had resulted in the non - provision of social amenities. These were some of the grievances the community had against him for which a mob gathered in front of his house shouting and hauling abusive words at him. They did not stop at that as they vandalized property and obstructed vehicular movement",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:149,question:"The commission charged with the conduct of federal 	elections in Nigeria between 2014 and 2015 is..........",option:{a:"Nec",b:"fedeco",c:"Inec",d:"Necon"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:176,question:"The private ownership of the means of production is a feature of",option:{a:"capitalism",b:"Socialism",c:"Communalism",d:"Communism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:61,question:"In democracy, lack of press freedom leads to the denial of freedom of",option:{a:"association",b:"expression",c:"movement",d:"voting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:6,question:"Interpersonal relationship exists when",option:{a:"citizens pay their taxes regularly to inland revenue service",b:"citizens are politically conscious and participate in voting",c:"there is interaction between persons in a social setting.",d:"groups share social interest and communal aspiration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:2,question:"Rule of Law means",option:{a:"supremacy of the law",b:"absence of legal immunity",c:"peace, order and stability",d:"obedience to any authority"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:204,question:"One of the ways to prevent the spread of HIV/AIDs is",option:{a:"Not to eat in fast food joints",b:"Not to shake hands with anybody",c:"To avoid any object contaminated with blood",d:"Sleep under a mosquito net"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:298,question:"Which of the following is not a preventive measure against the acquisition of the Ebola disease...........",option:{a:"Do not touch an infected person or their body fluids including blood, vomit, urine, saliva",b:"Wash your hands regularly with soap and water and apply sanitizers frequently",c:"Beware of hand shake and go for medical checkup as soon as possible when sick",d:"Do not bath with medicated soap"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:123,question:"The clause which exempts the president from being prosecuted while still in office is called",option:{a:"military clause",b:"special clause",c:"conviction clause",d:"immunity clause"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:162,question:"The ultimate aim of political parties is to",option:{a:"implement people oriented programmes",b:"acquire and exercise power",c:"increase the political awareness of the electorate",d:"formulate and implement policies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:304,question:"The Boko Haram insurgency started around",option:{a:"2009",b:"2014",c:"1960",d:"1963"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:340,question:"Decrees are laws made by .............",option:{a:"the parliament",b:"the judiciary",c:"the military",d:"senators"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:212,question:"The armed forces and the police are part of the ........ organ of government",option:{a:"executive",b:"judicial",c:"legislative",d:"informative"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:142,question:"From the basic road traffic regulation pedestrians should not attempt to cross the road when the light are ............. and ...............",option:{a:"green and yellow",b:"green and red",c:"yellow and red",d:"red and yellow"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:28,question:"One of the conditions which can limit the enjoyment of Human Rights in Nigeria is the",option:{a:"acceptance of foreign aid by the government",b:"improvement in literacy level of the citizens",c:"declaration of state of emergency by government",d:"periodic review of the constitution by government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:325,question:"A committee of PDP members is made up of 9 Hausas, 8 Igbo and 7 Yorubas. If the president wishes to choose just one person to be his special adviser, find the probability that the person chosen is neither Hausa nor Yoruba",option:{a:"7/24",b:"2/3",c:"3/8",d:"1/3"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:66,question:"Which of the following system of government advocates equitable distribution of wealth?",option:{a:"Aristocracy",b:"Capitalism",c:"Plutocracy",d:"Socialism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:331,question:"Those eligible to partake in the scheme are those",option:{a:"Those seeking for admission into the higher institutions",b:"Who have successfully completed their studies from higher institution .eg. college of education, 		     polytechnic & university",c:"Who are looking for something to keep them busy",d:"Who are from poor family background"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:67,question:"The right of an individual to seek redress in a law court is categorized under",option:{a:"economic.",b:"political",c:"procedural,",d:"social"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:191,question:"The function of vehicle inspection officer (VIO) is",option:{a:"ensuring the road wordiness of vehicle on the road",b:"protection of life and property",c:"collection of tax",d:"counting of votes cast at election"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:413,question:"The responsibility of empowering the youth rests mostly with",option:{a:"the political class",b:"religious organizations",c:"university administrators",d:"national government"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:238,question:"The rule of law simply means",option:{a:"The ruling of a lawful leader",b:"The absence of political instability",c:"Supremacy of the law",d:"The ruling of legislators"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:53,question:"The responsibilities of government to   its citizens include the following, except",option:{a:"creating employment opportunity",b:"maintenance of law and order",c:"payment of property tax to its citizens",d:"protection of lives and property"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:235,question:"The illegal sales and transportation of human beings for economic and some other selfish purpose is termed",option:{a:"Slave Trade",b:"Survival of the Fittest",c:"Gross Human Right Abuse",d:"Human Trafficking"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:424,question:"The foreign policy objective of Nigeria as enshrined in the 1999 Constitution exclude the promotion of",option:{a:"national interest",b:"African integration",c:"support for donor agencies",d:"just world economic order"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:69,question:"Which of the following is a legal obligation of a citizen?",option:{a:"Giving financial assistance to the poor",b:"Helping in community development",c:"Payment of taxes",d:"Respecting the national symbols"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:351,question:"“We the people of the Federal Republic of Nigeria” is usually the opening phrase of the preamble to",option:{a:"coup announcement",b:"government gazettes",c:"constitution",d:"mansard"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:18,question:"The principle that public servants cannot be held responsible for their official actions denotes",option:{a:"impartiality",b:"accountability",c:"anonymity",d:"neutrality."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:256,question:"Malaria fever can be transmitted through",option:{a:"hand shaking",b:"eating of unbalanced diet",c:"mosquito bite",d:"eating of bush meat such as bat and monkey"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:250,question:"When a constitution is difficult to amend it is said to be",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"written",d:"federal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:349,question:"Which of the following instruments is not used by a civil society group?",option:{a:"Propaganda",b:"Boycott",c:"Protest",d:"Violence"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:357,question:"Cultism can best be discouraged through",option:{a:"mentoring of cultists by the rich",b:"provision of jobs for cultists",c:"sensitization on the dangers of cultism",d:"establishment of cultists support groups"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:387,question:"The most important place for building good values is the",option:{a:"social welfare centre",b:"workplace",c:"family",d:"media houses"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:86,question:"Which of the following bodies is responsible for defending the country against external aggression? The",option:{a:"Army",b:"Civil defense.",c:"Customs.",d:"Police."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:389,question:"Which of the following statements may be true about the behaviour of the candidates in the diagram?",option:{a:"The candidates are doing what is ethical",b:"Candidates involved in malpractice should be banned for life",c:"Their action can also affect innocent candidates",d:"Their misconduct will guarantee a reliable certificate"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:302,question:"Which of these is NOT undesirable in the society",option:{a:"cultism",b:"terrorism",c:"patriotism",d:"vandalism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:296,question:"Public servants in Nigeria are expected to be .............",option:{a:"involved in politics",b:"non-partisan",c:"ambitious politically",d:"partial"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:40,question:"Which of the following governmental agencies is the most capable of controlling the activities of Wanja and his group?",option:{a:"National Agency for Food and Drug Administration and Control (NAFDAC)",b:"National Orientation Agency (NO A)",c:"National Emergency Management Agency (NEMA)",d:"National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA)"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:365,question:"Drug law enforcement agencies in Nigeria are not empowered to",option:{a:"execute drug suspects",b:"arrest drug barons",c:"prosecute drug traffickers",d:"rehabilitate drug addicts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:44,question:"When leaders like Chief Bilisi place self interest above public good, the result is that",option:{a:"rebellion becomes inevitable",b:"cooperation of citizens is guaranteed",c:"International support for the regime is ensured",d:"society becomes more peaceful and orderly."},section:"Chief Bilisi was a prominent politician and honourable minister in Kantoga Republic. He had sponsored several candidates to power and made them to swear oath of allegiance to him. In return, they awarded contracts and offered financial and material assistance to him at the expense of the public. This had resulted in the non - provision of social amenities. These were some of the grievances the community had against him for which a mob gathered in front of his house shouting and hauling abusive words at him. They did not stop at that as they vandalized property and obstructed vehicular movement",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:346,question:"Rates are collected in Nigeria by",option:{a:"Federal Inland Revenue Service",b:"State Ministry of Finance",c:"Local Government Councils",d:"Council of Traditional Rulers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:372,question:"One of reasons leaders fail to protect the interest of their followers is",option:{a:"selfishness",b:"inadequate finance",c:"ignorance",d:"rigid policies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:373,question:"Which of the following is not a form of political participation?",option:{a:"Taking part in voters’ registration exercise",b:"Voting during elections",c:"Joining political party",d:"Ballot box stuffing during elections"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:218,question:"Which one of the following is the founding father of Nigeria nationalism?",option:{a:"Goodluck Jonathan",b:"Oba Kosoko",c:"Herbert Macaulay",d:"Olusegun Obasanjo"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:125,question:"The following are causes of emergency rule except",option:{a:"crisis",b:"blood lettings",c:"stage peaceful protest",d:"sabotage / terrorism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:322,question:"General Murtala Mohammed was assassinated on his way to work in ..............",option:{a:"February 13, 1976",b:"June 12, 1993",c:"October 1, 1960",d:"June 8, 1998"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:108,question:"The form of government in which the electorate exercise their governing power directly through their elected 	representation is called ........",option:{a:"supremacy",b:"democracy",c:"autocracy",d:"charismatic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:251,question:"If Omonigho had taken the tablet one three times a day for six days his action constitutes a kind of",option:{a:"good drug administration",b:"drug abuse",c:"drug trafficking",d:"none of the abuse"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:73,question:"A political party’s programme is known as its",option:{a:"constitution.",b:"document.",c:"functions.",d:"manifesto."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:4,question:"Citizenship status is acquired through",option:{a:"birth, indigenization, colonization and referendum",b:"association, convention, naturalization and incorporation",c:"birth, naturalization, honorary and registration",d:"registration, inter-relationship, integration and declaration."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:49,question:"Cooperation between one country and another can be described as",option:{a:"bilateral",b:"international",c:"multilateral",d:"multinational."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:257,question:"Plenty of money in the society, not backed by commensurate productive activities can lead to",option:{a:"deflation",b:"inflation",c:"National developmental",d:"cashless society"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:232,question:"Public corporation are owned by the",option:{a:"government",b:"banks",c:"private individuals",d:"foreigners"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:23,question:"To prevent the spread of HIV/AIDS, people should be encouraged to",option:{a:"avoid casual sexual activities",b:"marry very early in life",c:"engage in gainful employment",d:"pursue higher education"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:283,question:"Consumers of ......... especially ........... and ..............stand the a great risk of contacting the Ebola disease",option:{a:"fish, tilapia, titus",b:"bush meat, monkey, bat",c:"meat, cow, dog",d:"vegetable, water leaf, bitter leaf"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:197,question:".............. was the capital of Nigeria before .................",option:{a:"Abuja - Lagos",b:"Lagos - Abuja",c:"Ikeja - Abuja",d:"Benin - Abuja"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:369,question:"Democracy thrives most where there is",option:{a:"nonpartisan judiciary",b:"freedom of speech and association",c:"absence of universal suffrage",d:"one-party system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:148,question:"The right of citizens to participate in the affairs of government of their country is called",option:{a:"economic right",b:"civil right",c:"political right",d:"social right"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:395,question:"The National Agency for Food and Drug Administration and Control (NAFDAC) was established in",option:{a:"1993",b:"1996",c:"1999",d:"2001"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:361,question:"Drug abuse can be prevented by",option:{a:"fighting drug addicts",b:"poverty reduction",c:"reducing drugs in circulation",d:"legal sanction"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:199,question:"The law is enforced by",option:{a:"Military",b:"Legislators",c:"Police force",d:"Area boys"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:222,question:"The ideology which emphasizes a classless society is",option:{a:"Communism",b:"Capitalism",c:"Totalitarianism",d:"Feudalism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:58,question:"One of the aims of citizenship education is to produce students with",option:{a:"creative skill.",b:"high sense of entrepreneurial skill.",c:"high sense of patriotism.",d:"manipulative skills."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:221,question:"An instrument for exercise of power for controlling, administering and managing the affairs of people based on laws is the",option:{a:"Civil service",b:"Executive",c:"Government",d:"State"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:405,question:"A major way of promoting responsible parenthood is through",option:{a:"sex education",b:"sound education",c:"population control measures",d:"tax reduction measures"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:76,question:"The headquarters of United Nations is located in",option:{a:"Abuja.",b:"England",c:"Hague.",d:"New York."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:174,question:"One judicial function performed by the executive is",option:{a:"granting of amnesty",b:"implementing judicial order",c:"ensuring obedience to the law",d:"appointing judges"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:376,question:"One of the major complaints against public service is",option:{a:"inefficiency",b:"understaffing",c:"victimization",d:"discrimination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:286,question:"The Ebola disease is usually acquired when a person comes in contact with",option:{a:"the blood or bodily fluids of an infested organism",b:"anybody whose name is Bola",c:"any animal",d:"snake fish"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:416,question:"HIV/AIDS is generally described as terminal in nature because it is",option:{a:"preventable",b:"transmittable",c:"avertable",d:"incurable"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:418,question:"A situation whereby someone is obliged to inform a superior about his actions and decisions for the purpose of control is",option:{a:"probity",b:"self-discipline",c:"accountability",d:"fair play"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:229,question:"The individual rights would be better protected if enshrined in the ..................",option:{a:"Courts",b:"Constitutions",c:"Bible and Quran",d:"National Newspapers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:370,question:"Rule of law is limited by the following except",option:{a:"state of emergency",b:"habeas corpus",c:"illiteracy",d:"immunity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:109,question:"Punishment for law breaking include the following except ..........",option:{a:"freedom of movement",b:"detention",c:"sanctions",d:"political instability"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:280,question:"Jamiu and Onome were among those standing inside a BRT bus in Lagos. Onome mistakenly stepped on Jamiu and Jamiu gave Onome a very dirty slap. As a law a biding citizen of the country which of the following reactions is expected of Onome",option:{a:"Turn the other chick for another slap",b:"Slap Jamiu back and prepare for any fight that might ensure",c:"Let Jamiu know that he, Onome stepped on him inadvertently, but pardon him to avoid escalating the matter",d:"Push Jamiu down from the moving bus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:410,question:"The NDLEA personnel are not usually found in",option:{a:"international airports",b:"seaports",c:"border crossings",d:"foreign embassies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:279,question:"A sovereign state is one",option:{a:"whose citizens are free to evade responsibility",b:"whose governments decisions are made independent of foreign interference",c:"which has a president and a prime minister",d:"where its citizens can speak without fear or favour"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"}],n={message:e,subject:o,status:200,total:120,data:i};export{i as data,n as default,e as message,a as status,o as subject,t as total};
